hello I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
biding on the podcast we discuss how AI
is changing both what apps do and how
they're built the relationship between
price and retention and why react native
apps monetize better than native hi
Jacob hi David it's your favorite time
of the year where we get to go on an
audio podcast and talk about charts so
2025 status subscription apps report I
will call out page numbers during the
podcast so might be good to go ahead and
download the report and listen to this
in front of the report I think the most
interesting and and probably the best
place to start is AI I mean that's no
I'm pretty sure that was our stick last
year so it was kind of like there's
something going on in artificial
intelligence well now it has gone on
yeah I I'm writing my intro for this
this afternoon but I now it's there's
something going on in artificial
intelligence prob going to be my tldr so
looking at the numbers and these are on
pages 143
189 and 58 you have to kind of pull a
few different charts together to look at
it we didn't do a slide kind of
comparing directly but I think the most
interesting thing about our AI app
breakdown is that the conversion rates
actually aren't that much different AI
apps aren't specially placed to drive
better conversions but what they do
really well is monetize the revenue per
user at the end of a year at the end of
a month is significantly higher on AI
than it is the rest of the app industry
this may be a little bit of a rising
tide floats all boats kind of situation
where people are starting to get a
little used to paying $20 a month for
something on their little pocket
computer you know may spill over a
little bit and continue to get people
comfortable paying for subscriptions I
mean I just think they're better as like
I it doesn't surprise me that the
conversion rate cuz like to some degree
the number of people who have the like
flexible income and willingness to spend
you know there's not that many marginal
people will buy an app but you know one
app but not another it's probably single
digit percentages regardless of the
content of that app but if the apps are
significantly better and just do
something more capital V valuable people
will pay more and they'll stay retained
longer you know I think this has been
too this related but the debate has been
where is the value going to crew in Ai
and I think something that's changed my
thinking from what last year to now so
last year I kind of thought well B2B
tends to be the big winner in a lot of
things right it's like they very sticky
you have apis it's whatever I thought
the consumer would be important but I
didn't really realize and it seems to be
this complete opposite is that the
Enterprise side to some degree or the
API side the dev tool side is very
easily swapped in and out and it's the
consumer layer it's the app layer you
know it's the brand that seems to be
where the differentiation is and the
modes are which is awesome that's great
for app developers right because that's
what you can bring everybody has access
to Cloud 3.7 but like you can bring
something unique in terms of like brand
and translation and things like that and
that's what's going to drive people to
convert and retain more than anything
else I've been thinking about this a lot
and I do think that the differentiation
piece is key though because if you just
Vibe code another like chat GPT rapper
everybody can Vibe code a chat GPT
wrapper yeah what have you done in that
case right you've not you've not
enhanced anything yeah you've not
created much value I think where we're
going to see certain apps really take
off is differentiation in that value
created so are you doing something like
unique and hard that's not able to just
be Vibe coded you know do you have some
like technological differentiation but
then secondarily it just kind of goes
back to distribution as differentiation
it's you know okay you Vibe coded a chat
TPT at but why should anybody care how
are you going to get attention for that
and then how are you going to stay
differentiated and retain those users
over time like what value are you really
driving that nobody else can drive and
that's kind of been true forever right
it's like there's a million apps on the
App Store like building the app has
never been like the hardest part is like
getting attention sustainably building a
community building up a user base that's
where the rubber really meets the road
there's always been a million apps like
now we're going to say there been 10
million apps I think that's why maybe it
may not seem like the entire the
individual experience of an app may not
change that much because even if the
economy of app spend is growing the
number of people rushing into the App
Store is also growing because the
barriers to build apps has gone down and
continues to go down which I think has
been the surprising thing to me is like
we're seeing new tools for one shotting
simple stuff which again simple stuff is
not probably going to make you any money
but like all complex and interesting
things start as simple things right and
so as we see these tools continue to
improve I think we'll see more
competition but I actually am not
convinced that that's going to cuz a
single vertical like some let's say rock
identification apps I don't know you
come pick some tiny like little niche I
think probably what will happen is we'll
just see actually more niches they're
not going to see 10 times the number of
rock identification apps we're going to
see 10 times new things that to a rock
identification app that we haven't even
thought about yet because like the
people that build that have not been
able to build apps yet and the barriers
have been too high and so this is
probably moot at this point in in March
2025 but like I I think it's a very
exciting time to be building apps that
are AI first that are doing novel things
and that's always been the case of
Technology like you make money by
building novel things that you know
nobody else does and sometimes that's
differentiated on the application of
technology sometimes that's on brand or
other things right but like people will
pay for something that they can't get
someplace else it's not a commodity or
Community as well like if you can one
shot a straa competitor which probably
going to be a while before you can even
if you could it's like they're so
differentiated on community and
leaderboards and like what do actually
people actually care about but that's
where there's probably opportunity to
create this sha for some Niche that's
not actually served well by straa and
you can create your own Community is it
going to be a billion dollar company
like or multi-billion dollar company
like sha probably not but can you make
good money building the the straa for a
smaller Niche there's only one Strava
before there's probably going to be one
straa after you know what I mean I
wouldn't let that stop you because you
can do 10 times more than the straa team
could I mean not the specifically but
like what it took to build that level
cruel of velocity 10 years ago is much
lower now and so I think the winnings
have not dropped down as much because
people yeah they're willing to spend
more for Absa do more so yeah it's a
good times the distribution as as
differentiation I think is going to
continue to be super important it's like
are you doing something so unique that
it can get attention on its own or is
that distribution as differentiation or
differentiation as
distribution I would say differentiation
as distribution right like it's your
differentiation is your distribution
maybe it means the same thing well that
that was kind of where I was going
though is that you can differentiate on
distribution like we're seeing a lot of
apps get really good at Tik Tok and
other channels I would say that's a
distribution as differentiation I would
argue there's also differentiation as
distribution where just being so unique
and strange like distribution just kind
of takes care of itself because you're
the one app that can do the thing right
ideally you have both though is so you
have some like unique lever to get
attention for your app and then it does
something unique that you can I was just
thinking about the Tik Tok example on
the hook right it's like if you make an
app that is like the the dump bunch at
gbt rappers again whatever you could do
that again it's like oh it's just
somebody asking an AI a question like
that's so 2023 nobody cares anymore but
if you have something magic and cool
that for a community on like like Tik
Tok can go viral now yes the
distribution is like unique there but
making the Tik Tok is not the hard part
necessarily it's coming up with
something that's like a unique value
prop that's going to like create
something that like an influencer can
talk about or even just goes viral on
its own that's really like thinking
about some sort sort differentiating
product feature that'll drive growth one
of the things I do think is different in
2025 though is that as you were talking
about we're going to have a 10 million
apps in the next few years instead of a
million it does seem like there's a
whole new crowd of folks who are just
watching ing any app that goes viral any
app that crosses 10K in Revenue a month
you know they're watching sensor Tower
app figures to watch for the apps that
are making any money and so as soon as
you start making any money like there's
going to be a rush of clones and then
that gets back to the point it's like
are you doing something that is
reasonably differentiated can you
differentiate fast enough or can you
gain market share enough fast enough to
where they're not really a threat or can
you continue to get attention for it
through paid through social through
whatever that's going to keep you ahead
of the curve when that flood of CopyCat
apps comes I mean I think this is why
it's still good to be really good at
software so like even if you're like
Vibe coding everything like if you're
really good at product and software
you'll still have an advantage over
somebody who has because everybody has
the same tools so whatever
differentiating skill set you have or
knowledge you have is going to I still
think matter going forward some of that
is also just like better understanding
those communities so like if there's a
community that you really understand in
a unique way literally knowing people
right like humans right which AI has yet
to really do or have a following in the
community you know we have seen a rise
in influencer Le apps where the
influencer has a following in a specific
area like macera is a really good
example they're a food logging app and
it's actually I think a collection of
multiple influencers who worked on that
app and so they just have that kind of
built-in community that they can market
to I mean you see this in product like
physical products as well like
everybody's launching with like you know
an influencer co-brand thing right as a
supplement yeah yeah exactly it's like
it's like a how do we take an
undifferentiated commodity essentially
and like you know create some sort of
margin while we attach put Mr BEAST's
face on it or whatever he owns all his
stuff first party but yeah and then most
of those do tap out because you tap out
your audience fairly quickly but then
you still then have to like once you hit
that Plateau then you got to figure out
like what's that next step product
differentiation distribution
differentiation you got to start paying
for ads you got to start like figuring
things out all right well I think that's
that's probably enough on AI the next
thing I wanted to talk about was App
Store visous Play Store so we do have
some interesting data this year that I
think further puts into charts what we
kind of all knew is that iOS just Far
and Away makes way more Revenue than
Play Store the interesting thing I saw
in our data though is that when you look
at the realized LTV chart the people who
do pay on Android do seem to actually
pay relatively similarly and so it does
seem like based on the data we're
sharing in the report that it really is
just a bigger problem of there are more
payers on iOS than it is like the
Android users are that price sensitive
the question is like do they meet this
like whatever ability to spend money on
Tiny software apps or whatever and
that's like sort of invariant to what
kind of phone they have but if they are
that kind of person is very correlated
with what kind of phone they have which
has kind of always been known I don't
know anecdotally I feel like I've been
seeing more people speaking well about
Android and some monetization stuff I
don't know if we have any data support
that but I've seen more people seem
optimistic but like all the big apps we
know are still investing in Android the
popularity of flutter react native like
all these crossplatform things I still
think make the building for Android
easier and potentially worthwhile but I
still think that like you should never
invest any incremental effort into
building for that platform until you're
of other higher leverage ideas or you
think it's like going to create some
Network effect to have it on both
platforms I think where folks are
starting to find better monetization on
Android is diversifying into hybrid
monetization and some other slides we'll
talk about in a minute but I do wonder
if the realized LTV being similar across
IOS and Android and there being more
pairs might actually be an artifact of
too many apps just copying and pasting
their iOS strategy and that maybe next
year we'll see the realized LTV for
Android users drop as folks experiment
with those lower prices with adjusting
Regional pricing and things like that
the people that I'm hearing find more
success on Android are doing those kind
of experiments like I talked to Tammy
from Google on one of the minisodes
leading up to the release of the report
and they've been sharing a lot of data
which is really fascinating and some of
the data they shared was that they see
way better monetization on Android with
hybrid monetization it's like give
people their option to pay for one
feature or if you're a Content app like
let him just buy that piece of content
yeah more monetizing that like if you
have one single price point basically
everybody who doesn't hit that price
point is thrown away so they generate
Zero versus like have some price
discrimination some products on the way
down so that like you can monetize and
if that area under that curve is big
enough it can be substantial I think
also one thing we don't capture in our
data is like ads monetization which you
know if you have a lot of people who
don't have a lower prival to pay like
advertising or monetizing eyeballs is a
good way to do it but which we don't
necessar have data on but that might be
you know I I've certainly heard of and
seen more cases of that like to improve
your like total LTB is like to be
running ads which is like essentially
what you're saying it's like a hybrid
monetization but not just I AP hybrid
but like adding other things to generate
Revenue unfortunately on Android the
cpms are really low as well but I I was
talking to Demitri again another
minisode that we did leading out to this
report and one of the things he shared
was that because ad rates are so low in
some of these developing nations and on
Android specifically that by adjusting
their price significantly lower maybe
even lower than you would expect in some
of these Regions they're actually seeing
good return on ad span because ads are
so cheap it's cheap on both sides so you
can afford to drop your price on Android
Andor in some of these developing
nations so the example he gave was
Brazil it's like the way they finally
cracked ad spend in Brazil was just by
dramatically dropping their prices in
Brazil because the ads are so cheap that
they could afford to monetize it's a
good lesson in just like how much
optimization that work there is in these
kind of businesses right if you want to
keep driving and I think it's somewhat
unique in that sense in terms of like
different industries that that there are
so many consumers in so many different
locals and it goes to show too like it's
not one single variable right it's like
okay you got to think of the whole
ecosystem it's not just the like
conversion part it's the acquisition
part you want to be testing those things
jointly if you possibly can yeah super
interesting stuff I did promise to share
page numbers so that's like Pages 113
116 hopefully the page numbers will say
the same it's going I was going to ask
if that's the case we'll just say is in
that area yeah if we end up adding or
removing a page might shift one by one
in the
oneish the next section that I found
super interesting was the hybrid versus
native and this is on page 125 is is
that react native performs really well
can't stop it well not the first hybrid
framework but you know maybe the first
biggest one or whatever but uh yeah it's
still very popular I'm going to do a
podcast with the uh the founder of Expo
not too long from now I almost did it as
a minone I thought it'd be fun to
actually do a full episode on it but
Expo works with react native it's kind
of a you can explain it better clci kind
of yeah Expo just like it makes react
hosting and deploying react native apps
much much easier so I thought it was
super super interesting because all of
us snoody Indie developers are like
native or
GTFO customers don't care they can't
tell like you're a connoisseur of apps
David but like I do think for we'll use
flighty as an example I think if you're
like heading into a crowded market and
you product is differentiation and
distribution having it being finally
crafted and perfectly tuned is your
product then like I probably wouldn't
use react native but like if that's not
what your differentiation is like it's a
great option and they're going to have a
moment I think they already are Expo
included which is like most of these
like models are really good at speaking
in JavaScript and typescript for
building these things I just played with
a service yesterday where it like one
shot I have been working on this like
stargazing side project for the longest
time and I never got anywhere I'm my
brain scattered and it just never came
together you're a CEO of a company you
don't have time to be running a side
projects no I I I have the time I don't
have the talent is the problem I don't
know how to write Swift anymore but yeah
it almost one shot it like pretty dang
close like it had some other stuff but
like got like a lot of it and did it
with react native because yeah I guess
the models see a lot of react as well so
they they're good at it but anyway the
thing that react native and we're
talking about you know flutter as well
like there's those of these but what
they've always been good at is like the
person that doesn't necessarily know how
to write Swift Swift's a compiled
language like you got to have a Mac
which like most people do but like not
everybody and like it's not you know
there's a lot of advantages to like the
person who's not like a Mac or iOS
person maybe don't seem all that
important and so I think the AI tools
are going to continue to drive these
things give a second win like for the
longest time flutter was gaining on
react native I think like also Google's
kind of maybe pulled back on their
Investments some flutter they also have
cotton multiplatform which we didn't
break out in the report but that's
gaining steam as well which is just like
as a Meta Meta Meta we're still
investing in tooling for apps which is
great he's I guess it's my job to jump
up and be like the Mobile's not over but
like it's clearly not because like we're
still investing in multiple different
ways to do things and re natives
advancing and flutters being worked on
every day and I I mean flutter people
are obsessed too like God bless them but
like people who use flutter are really
fanatic about it but yeah it's good and
I used to like you David I used to I
think be a little more snoody about it
but now I'm like hey like if your
differentiation is not the things that
native is better at which is like you
know fit and finish down to the
pixel there's a lot of advantages to
doing these and like I think it's worth
considering CU you can always like if it
does come to the point where you need a
native rewrite and you're at scale you
can afford to do that it's it's usually
not the end of the world I was talking
to a friend recently who's like super
super bullish on building apps with AI
one these he told me that actually makes
a ton of sense once you think about it
is that one of the benefits of using
reactor flutter but specifically react
with something like cursor is that it
can actually run the app and like
screenshot it and iterate on the UI and
test for bugs without having to run the
simulator and like all this crap that's
the thing I was using yesterday it's
like in a browser and like to run a
native IOS app in a it' be impossible
like that would just be like really
really difficult but yeah just works
basically with some shimming and things
like that so yeah it's kind of
interesting it's like these Technologies
you know Expo has been around a long
time expo's been around since at least
2016 is when I first like started using
it and you know just chugging along and
then suddenly a general purpose
technology appears and their their whole
like landscape changes which is really
cool take away from this section I think
we've already had quite a few but if you
are just getting started or you're like
building a new app and trying to explore
new avenues and react is a great place
to build right now because makes it way
easier and then as we show in the report
it doesn't mean you're going to monetize
more poorly so if your differentiation
is community if your differentiation is
distribution like you have some unique
angle you're serving a niche and you
want to be on both platforms especially
but even if you just want to be on iOS
like it's probably a really good place
to start today day it can reduce time to
Market and like iteration time depending
on what talent you have on your team as
well like if you don't have the skill
set if you're not a swift developer but
you can do JavaScript like do it this
way it'll be worth it be worth the
tradeoffs all right now on to some bad
news page 70ish in the report is we did
look at retention this year compared to
last year and last year we compared to
2023 2023 to 2022 and what we looked at
is year one retention compared 2024
compared to 2021 and it's trending
downward and it was trending downward in
our last report and I think it was even
trending downward from our very first
report I think that's just to be
expected more apps more people spending
money there's more competition every
year right like it gets and the numbers
aren't like drastic you know it's still
in the 40s or 30s to 40s through that
period but like yeah it makes sense like
we talked a bunch about the barriers to
building apps is going down people are
becoming more Discerning with what apps
they choose and it doesn't mean you
can't build good long retaining cohorts
cuz there are people who still fall in
love with your app it just probably
there's some folks on the margins who
are going to get stolen away by more
competitors and more options and things
like that so yeah things get harder over
time I think this is also maybe an
artifact of the fact that more people
are spending more money on apps as well
and so when you have so many more people
willing to pay so many more apps
launching and people getting better at
monetization if you're driving more of
those incremental
users who don't have as high of intent
and you're monetizing them better then
you are probably going to turn more of
those users and so as the techniques for
monetizing have improved I think that's
maybe part of it as well it's like apps
are monetizing better than ever which
then kind of converting better than ever
which then leads to higher turn yeah
there is always anytime you push on one
part of the funnel you're going to just
going to pop out on another part yeah
exactly the heavier you push you know
onboarding and really optimizing that
early funnel you should expect a drop
off in the late funnel in renewals and I
think our data just shows that so the
next one is monthly Revenue one year
after launch so this is page 63 is I
thought this was really interesting you
know we at Revenue cat are kind of an
index of the entire app industry all the
way from chat gbt being a customer down
to like my side projects the headline
here is that
just 5% of apps are making over 9,000 a
month a year after launch or around
9,000 a month let me rephrase that David
5% of apps are making $99,000 a month or
more I think it's it could be looked at
either way but yeah that's true but you
know as we hit a 10 million apps like
what is that going to look like yeah
how's that going to change but it means
like 10x right by the way 1 to 10
million I don't know if that number is
right but it's going to go up like it's
going to increase one out of 20 apps
makes enough within its first year to
sustain at least one person
which is pretty cool I mean you know
that's a lottery ticket like would you
go buy a lottery ticket if you knew like
one in 20 chance this would become like
a sustaining annuity like you know like
that's pretty dang good I'd probably buy
a lot of those I mean obviously they're
expensive to build an app and try it
we've always known this it's like fairly
cheap to like make a basic and and like
I wish we could like survey customers
when they fill out their app like are
you serious about this like take off the
people who are just building stuff for
fun they kind of like see and then like
but the fun thing about this industry is
that there's not really a solid line
between those things right like things
start off as side projects and they
bubble and they get big and like most of
the times they don't and that's what
kind of makes this fun a fun company to
work at or like industry to work in but
yeah I mean I don't know do you read
that David and it feels demoralizing a
little bit or well you're right that
it's both demoralizing and encouraging
if you're building a brand new app and
you're not funded you don't have a ton
of money to spend on acquisition and
kind of getting that early funnel going
you should recognize this it's still
just hard like for all the like tweets
about how easy it is to build an app and
make it go around on Tik Tok it's hard
it's easier to write a thread about it
that's for sure exactly but yeah I guess
I guess this is the same version of my
last question I'd love to know like
relative the inputs though like how much
did those people actually try besides
like building app did they actually go
market did they actually like try to
build like a little bit of a growth Loop
or have some sort of sense of how to
grow it and like how many of these were
apps that like ever in a million years
could do that right like oh I made a you
know tracking app for people who knit
sweaters for dogs I don't which maybe is
a a big Market but like there are
sometimes apps that are so Niche it's
like they'll never make money not cuz
they're bad apps just cuz like the
market is not there cuz yeah it would be
interesting to qualify it a bit more but
yeah there's money to be made and then
as the effort goes down too I mean for
folks who've got a a job you know making
500 bucks a month that's like a car
payment you know that's a nice side
hustle I had like a windows that made
$1,000 a month for years was like the
best thing very low maintenance and so
yeah even even absent of it becoming a
full-time thing it's like it's a
worthwhile investment for a lot of
creators and makers and stuff like this
so but you were saying earlier like the
longer we've worked at Revenue C like
I'm closing on 6 years you're at like 8
years I was telling somebody yesterday I
was looking back at some of my earliest
office hours so when I joined in 2019
one of the first things I did was like
to set up an open Thursday where anybody
could book time on my calendar and it is
crazy to look back at some of those
early office hours calls and like those
apps are huge now like I talked to
Monarch money now they're a funded
company and everything like that but I
talked to them like in October of 2019
and they're like a 100% company now
doing really well I mean you know they
caught a break right and I think the
commonality is they tried like they took
it there's probably like a real highly
selective thing there to somebody who
takes an office hours with Revenue cat
maybe more so than like their necessary
idea or particular tactics but they were
just putting the energy in I would have
expected more customers to die not
physically but like they've proven a lot
of longevity right I mean even if
they're not hyper Growers and like
they're not on their way to become the
next straa or whatever then yet they
grow like you know you figure out a
little bit year-over year and then
depending on if you raise you know
that's where you get can get gummed up
is if you raise money or not but if
you're building an app that you care
about that you're passionate about
that's you think is solving a problem or
whatever whatever motivates you these
businesses can be pretty sticky and
durable and yeah you might not be a set
up to return ADV Venture investor 100x
their money but just don't take their
money and like you're good I know I feel
like I've been talking to more and more
Indies who are like ah I'm like so close
to quitting my day job and then you know
we've had multiple people on the podcast
where things started off as a side
project and then year over year you know
just that compounding growth I mean
slopes is maybe a good example they're
not a customer but like their company
continues to grow in scale and started
off kind of as a little project one
person project a manual at card pointers
who we've featured a lot in our from our
marketing and stuff this kind of a one
onean show with some help but like
continues to like do a lot with a little
and grow and grow you know they all have
in common that they've built something
great of course all right then next
section to cover is monetization BS I
thought this was another really
interesting slide page 44 is it just
shows that lots of apps are starting to
finally experiment with hybrid
monetization so we kind of break down
subscriptions only versus subscriptions
with consumables subscriptions plus
Lifetime and then subscription
consumables and Lifetime and that last
one's fairly minimal and we've had a ton
of talks I'm still pretty bearish on
Lifetime like I was going to bring this
up on the last slide is that the magic
of subscriptions is that if you do build
something valuable you are creating a
new nity it's like if people are using
it day in and day out they could be
using it for a decade and that's what an
app like slopes and some of these other
apps that have built year over year over
year part of that build is delivering
value and then people continuing to pay
year after year so you're not having to
reacquire your users all over again like
we did back in the paid up front days
and so time we could have a whole
another talk on I don't think for most
apps it's a great choice except for
maybe early on where you know you do
just kind of pull some Revenue forward
but you know we're seeing more and more
apps mixing consumables as well in our
data gaming of course is the largest
category that is experimenting with
subscriptions plus consumables no
surprise but you see it across all
categories now I mean from business and
education to Social and lifestyle photo
and video 133% I think that's maybe
could be related to credits like that's
probably driving that as well a lot more
apps of selling AI credits or like Photo
credits to like cover their cost on the
back them and that's actually a great
example too of where I think consumables
make a ton of sense for AI is that you
know you're going to have a small number
of users who are going to create outsize
costs yeah and like trying to fully
estimate what you need to charge and
your subscription might be not worth the
effort right versus like just tracking
and giving away for people to buy more
credits it's a little more work but like
it's totally doable I've an again
anecdotally heard more and more of this
like people cuz I think we are in some
ways we're late stage subscriptions
right like kind of people know the basic
tricks it's like you get trials and do
an annual if you can and then you get
this the web stuff set up and then you
get the like retention campaigns like so
people are pushing into like okay what's
the next like incremental thing we can
add and there's a lot of apps out there
that the way they're structured there's
opportunities to charge on some sort of
consumable basis it's a good way to to
you know make sure your people who want
to spend more can it's kind of annoying
to build like a consumables like in
credits tracking and currencies or
whatever but we're working on some
tooling and some apis to make it much
much easier to like have consumables and
then track a ledger of currencies and
things like that that I think actually
will potentially allow people to again
experiment because it's like it might
work it might not it's a big buildout so
if we can let you try it for like a you
know an order of magnitude cheaper I
think more people can probably find some
gains there yeah really just makes a ton
of sense what I have been seeing in in
some of these AI apps is that you pay a
subscription and you get a certain
number of credits and if you run out of
credits you can buy more credits and
that's like a super kind of natural
thing the one thing I will say I saw one
app that was doing this and it was
getting slammed in the reviews because
the subscription was actually fairly
expensive but it included so few credits
that people felt kind of rug pulled it
was like wait I can only like create
three images and now now I got to start
paying for credits you still have to
like deliver that value and it has to be
kind of a fair exchange for people so if
you're charging 20 bucks a month it's
like people got to feel like they're
getting their $20 of value before you
can charge those consumables on top and
you use that money because you know the
people who don't use as many calls you
have to use their unused credits to pay
for other people's right and you have to
kind of understand that risk you take
some risk there but yeah I I expect this
to get more I think we're not I think
we're early days on this in a lot of
apps so all right the next section I
wanted to cover is time to trial and so
this is Page 13ish very early in the
report you we've kind of talked about
this a lot over the last few years and I
don't think we compared last year to
this year maybe we didn't even share
this data in last year's report but it
does seem like more and more apps are
pushing to start that free trial very
early putting that pay wall in the
onboarding and so what we see across all
of the ABS and revenue cat is over 80%
of trial starts happen that first day
they open the app which is just crazy
and you would hope too that the whole
idea with premium like get people using
the product and then eventually they're
going to convert yeah you get the last
20% on every day after that but yeah so
such as the nature you get one shot
people are going to make their buying
decision trialing decision and just like
that's where the most people are but I
think most people have they have how
they think the world works and then
there's how the world works and like
this is a good example of that certainly
this is the only conversion point you
should be thinking about out as you
start your monetization you know and
that's why like even people just not
like not having the pay wall in the
onboarding is like such an L such an own
goal right it's like and everybody's
like I don't want to it's like no I
think this is an opinion I don't hear as
much anymore I think everybody's kind of
gotten it and I think our numbers show
that yeah yeah yeah but that's why you
just got to show it you know people
might not convert it's fine but like you
got to put it up there cuz like it might
be your only chance and if you're not
convinced yet to put your uh pay in
onboarding go look at this chart and
look at just how I mean it's hard to
communicate on an audio podcast just how
dramatic this chart looks 80% of all
trial starts happen in that first day
the chart's just crazy similar to that
the next page I want to look at is Page
92 the cancellation timeline and this is
the first time we've shared this in the
report and another one was kind of
unexpected to me just how much of churn
happens immediately like as soon as that
first charge hits their bank account the
month one churn shopping is the highest
and it's over 40% so maybe just to
explain this a little better the way we
kind of created the stat is for an
annual plan when does somebody go turn
off auto renew and ultimately turn so
people can turn it on and off back and
forth and we don't track that when do
they turn it off the last time so like
when is the kind of like final turn
decision and when you look at this chart
it's like most of that turn decision
most of that turning off auto renew
happens the first month I always
expected and we had pulled these numbers
internally and I think Eric Crowley from
GP bullhound he actually shared a
version of this chart in his report last
fall I expected the last month to be
like a huge Spike and it is a spike but
people are turning off auto renew that
first month and then it kind of like
slows down where like yes every month
people are checking the App Store
turning it off it's a relatively small
Spike most of the categories that we
broke out it's just around 10% maybe 10
12% some below 10% 27% or something like
that of customers will cancel in that
first month the next most common month
is the last month which kind of makes
sense it's to and like there are
distinct events but by far it's that
first month right which I guess you know
makes sense but I always thought it it's
like that's when Apple sends the email
like that's when the next charge is
going to come I think a lot of consumers
are just and I do this like if it's an
app I know I'm probably I don't intend
to build a lifelong relationship with
I'll buy it and I'll just go ahead and
cancel right away just so that I I know
yes I know I I shouldn't be doing this
to all the conversion rates out there
but it depends on the app right I think
people see the charge in their bank
account that's what's really driving
this because once you've actually paid
and it hits the bank account that's when
you're like oh yeah like maybe I don't
want to pay next year versus the
reminder that it's coming up like you've
kind of already made that decision all
right the next section I want to cover
is Google churn surveys this is really
interesting so again a new chart that
we've never shared before page 89 is
it's super fascinating when you turn on
Google Play I don't know exactly if it
comes with an app or if it's like
something it's sent bya email there's a
survey they send and then developers can
access that data you know this is
something we overlooked for a while but
in the past year we've started
collecting and surfacing that data so
that's why it's in the report for the
first time this year yeah and so as you
would expect the two biggest ones are
cost related so like just don't want to
pay and then not enough usage which is
the almost the same answer right it's
like the value equation does not balance
out you it's not worth it it's basically
you can combine those two and technical
issues found a better app other it's all
pretty small the competitive argument
maybe isn't all that valid this is like
sub 10% of people are switching to a
competitor and maybe who knows like how
people are answering this but like most
people are just they're not falling in
love with another app they're falling
out of love with your app right or maybe
their need has passed which is probably
a big chunk of it right like it's worth
right thinking about that in terms of
like if you want to build something
really big you want to build an app that
people kind of need all the time or like
continuously forever versus like even
Fitness or whatever it's like people
have an interest in a specific thing for
a minute and then they could kind of get
off of it the more you can build towards
something that can become a lifelong
habit and a lifelong practice like
you're going to just have better numbers
but still if people aren't using it
they're not going to keep paying so yeah
and if they're not finding enough value
and I'll mix this in we can maybe talk
about both of these simultaneously
because I think they're highly related
is that on page
71 we shared a breakdown of retained
subscribers after year one by price
point and this chart is super
fascinating to me and super relevant I
think to this price being a barrier is
that lower priced apps have way better
retention than higher price apps and it
just makes sense I think I actually made
a mistake in my weather app I was trying
to kind of push the boundary a little
bit and charge $40 a year for a weather
app where most weather apps are more in
the like 20 to $25 range and my turns
not terrible I think I'm going to end up
around 40% this year of retained
subscribers so 60% turn which is it's
above median like it's fine but I think
I would have done way better both on
conversion and retention with the lower
price point but you might not have made
more money so like you have to think
that through right like ratios don't
matter necessarily you got to like think
of what it's scaling against it might be
a worthy tradeoff but for weather app I
just can't help but think and for tons
of apps it's like when it's like oh it's
only 20 bucks and yeah I'm still kind of
using it here and there it's like it's a
way different decision if it's 20 bucks
versus 40 versus 60 versus 100 it's like
when a $20 thing is going to hit your
bank account it's like H yeah I mean
this is just a view on elastic demand
curves right like the higher price
something is like fewer people are going
to buy it but like you got to play
around with that price curve so yeah I'm
not sure I mean I think you're probably
right certainly like your renewal rate
would go up and your your conversion
rate would go up but like if you have
the price would both of those more than
double definitely not your conversion
rate probably or your renewal rate
probably wouldn't more than double not
more than double right conversion rate
would have to go up and then renewal
rate goes up again it's like what kind
of business are you trying to build and
last year my thought was well I'm going
to ramp up some ad spend and so having
the higher price point is going to make
the ad spend easier to make work but
then as those users start turning this
year like did I really make the right
choice and so combining those two charts
that a lot of people not enough us
combined with cost related is that
people are making financially rational
decisions how much value is your app
really delivering in their life and this
is where you as an app developer have to
be realistic and kind of like weigh all
of these things is like how much value
am I really delivering how much are they
willing to pay for that value and it's
not always like a great AB test either
right and you have to wait a whole year
to understand TR have you run one David
have you experimented with a different
price yeah I've done different price
experimentation I mean here's the hard
thing though unless you're like a really
big app and you've got your user
acquisition died in it's like a lot of
my traffic last year was from press and
so that cohort's going to perform really
differently than the average cohort and
then I knew that that cohort would
perform really differently than if I did
start ramping up ad span and so you know
as much as we talk about AB testing and
like finding the right price through
data it's like that's not always a great
way unless you kind of already have the
rest of the picture pretty dialed in
where you have a consistent cohort of
people coming from a consistent like ad
spend or a consistent source of
attention and I didn't have that and so
again like when you're early it probably
is just better to price it lower and
then like let those retentive cohorts
build up even if you're not price
maximizing until you build it to the
point where you're really delivering a
ton of value that's true like if you
were trying to build like a base of
happy paying subscribers is maybe it's
not a bad idea to let more people in
early especially if the cost of service
them is low there's some benefit there
and definitely worth looking at this I
mean definitely worth looking at all the
charts but go look at this chart page 71
it's pretty dramatic looking at just how
much better lower priced apps retain and
correlation is not causation you could
have a high price app that retains
incredibly well because you're
delivering a ton of value but if on
average you think about that cost
equation and the whole like subscription
fatigue thing I mean I could talk an
hour about my theories on that consumers
just don't want to pay for anything 98%
of your customers don't yeah nobody
wants to pay so I think a lot of
consumer subscription fatigue and the
kind of the meta around that is just
like the reality of consumers like
nobody wants to pay for anything people
complain about the price of gas but the
higher the more value per dollar you're
able to deliver to your customers the
better that looks and feels to them like
if you're delivering consumer surplus
they feel like it's a good deal you're
more likely to tell their friends
they're more likely to stay subscribed
yeah yeah yeah than NPS that promoter
score will go up right cuz they'll just
be like they want to you want to tell
your friends about a good deal right if
you're like really pushing the price to
the Limit and you've got this really
expensive app relative the value you're
delivering and this is where like
different categories like I brought up
ladder a bunch I did a minod with Greg
the CEO my wife uses it and it's 30
bucks a month it's one of the more
expensive apps generally but is a really
good app my wife hates technology she
hates ABS it's like she's like the exact
opposite of me she complains all the
time about tech failing her and like you
couldn't pry ladder from her cold dead
hands it's the only like Fitness thing
she's ever actually enjoyed and so like
they're delivering a ton of value they
have incredible retention and a really
high price so it's not that you can't
charge it's just that you just need to
really figure out where you sit on that
curve and if you're not delivering
enough value and in my Niche it's like a
billion weather apps out there and a
bunch of them are free and there's one
right in the the Apple weather is free
to anybody on an iPhone and so the
relative like value I'm able to deliver
probably isn't as high as something like
ladder that's able to deliver this
really differentiated experience in a
category where people are willing to
spend more so I think you got to kind of
take all of those into account but
looking at these two different charts it
should help people maybe rethink where
they land on that curve and like making
sure they are landing on the right spot
on that curve and then relatedly the
last slide I have to talk about today is
81 active renewal rates this is a
fascinating one I kind of argued with
our data scientist Rick who kind of
headed up the report these last couple
of years the way we calculate this is
that has a user interacted with the app
within the time frame of the renewal so
this skews a little bit because if
you're on a Weekly subscription did you
use it that week if you're on a a
monthly subscription did you use it that
month if you're on an annual
subscription did you use it that year so
this does kind of skew the numbers a
little bit but it is fascinating to see
weekly subscriptions like so few people
who renew actually used it within that
week but weeks are also very short right
so like versus the monthly it's more in
the like 60s 50s 40 to 60% of people use
it that's kind of natural though right
it's like they've probably stopped using
it I'm actually surprised it's that high
because that's usually for me the signal
just unsubscribe from something it's
like did I even use it this month like
no okay like I should probably
unsubscribe so it's kind of surprising
me that almost half of it on monthly
like they actually did use it in that
month but they still decided to not keep
it going it does go to the to the fact
that you will have a certain number of
users who aren't actively using your app
who are going to renew and again if
you're $20 a year and they're only using
it a few times a year like maybe that's
a fair exchange of value but if you're
$30 a month like ladder and you go a
couple of months without using it that
hits a little harder so it is is really
interesting to look at these numbers on
how active people are in that renewal
cycle on the annual side it's almost
100% of people use it in that period but
prior the whole year but there are a few
so there's a couple people who like get
charged didn't even use it for the whole
damn year before that's pretty rough
every year I feel like there's like 10
different charts it's like next year
we're going to do this a little
different because it would be
interesting 400 page SOA report why not
you know we can dream big yes it's like
250 this year for those who haven't
cracked the p F yet oh I assume
everybody listening has looked at every
single page so I would hope so at this
point but it would be fun to kind of
break this down with a little more
granularity to kind of understand the
usage patterns of those renewal cohorts
like a year is a long time kind of like
you said like have they used it within
that entire year yes but then like how
much are they using it when like how
what's the recency right yeah I think
that'd be really interesting for next
year there's probably some interesting
ways to cut this that would maybe
eliminate a bit more the usage Trend
before cancellation yeah you could do a
heat map of like usage up to for
canceled users or something like this I
don't know I can catch something out
something tough to approved well those
were my I didn't even count I probably
should have numbered these it's top
10ish yeah top 10ish on pages 11 14ish
through
whatever you know it's more about the
gist than it is about the accuracy which
is kind of true for this report period
it's like there's a lot in there it's
dare I say dense but it's an honest
report the numbers are real we spent a
lot of time on them we stand behind them
and yeah I think like don't read any one
data point and go change your whole
strategy but like take it read it give
you guys some basis some things to try
some new ideas for 2025 and it's always
helpful to look at peers and and I think
we have like the only data set like this
in the world and I'm glad we can share
it with everybody so well I think it's a
great place to wrap up I mean we could
probably talk another 20 minutes on like
how to use report and how not to use
report we talk about AI again no okay
we've covered this on other podcasts a
great podcast to listen to in
conjunction with this one is the most
recent Phil Carter episode where we
talked about his subscription value Loop
calculator so in that episode we did do
a much deeper dive on how to use
benchmarks when to use benchmarks when
not to use benchmarks and all the ideas
and theory behind that and it was a good
summary you you gave like the 60-second
summary like don't change your business
on one number in the St of subscription
apps report and that's true but there's
also a ton more Nuance around like what
decisions should you make based on this
data and how do you look at that data
and yeah we could go whole another hour
but we've already done that so go back
and listen to the uh subscription value
Loop calculator episode with Phil Carter
back in uh December of 2024 as kind of a
adjunct to this report but that's about
all I had to talk about is this our
third one David third Sosa podcast third
yeah third report third podcast yeah
it's better every year super fun 250
Pages something only a Management
Consultant could love I think anybody
who works in app love this report David
you can take that to the bank I wasn't
quite as involved this year as I had
been in years past because I was really
focusing on the the podcast minisodes
which if you haven't listened to those I
did 12 short really dense we've been
releasing one episode a day leading up
to the report and I personally edited
each one to make him as dense as
possible as much uh kind of time devalue
as possible but yeah reading through the
port this year I got to read through it
almost like a user
or like somebody else in the industry
versus like working on the numbers day
in day out for the last 3 months it was
a fun read as fun as a book of charts
can be candlesticks are back I thought
that was a nice touch you know this is
like inside rag or inside Soo with David
and Jacob you we just talk inside
baseball about it all day but yeah we're
proud of it I think you'll find some
insight so definitely worth and we've
got more contributors than before we
actually shared some data from apps
flyer and paddle kind of Partners who
shared some data we break down AI apps
so yeah there's a lot in there and uh
you're probably not going to read it
very few people in the world will will
sit there and read Page by Page all 250
pages keep a copy on your desk under
your pillow at the kitchen table four or
five copies scattered throughout the
house in the restroom just kind of
everywhere I
think yeah print it out just kill some
trees yay you're going to need a
thousand pages to get four copies so
well if you do doublesided depends what
kind of PR you have but anyways it was
uh really fun chatting through this with
you Jacob and looking forward to next
year and go download the report if you
haven't already with all these this fun
chat for an hour of listening remc.com
report right of course and the links in
the show notes all those things okay
cool see you next
year thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community
[Music]